<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shannon Burns</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Shannon Burns</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>/talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides</title>
      <link>/slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/slides/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link></link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid></guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Courses</title>
      <link>/courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/courses/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interpersonal Communication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful communication between people necessarily requires that the ideas from my mind make it into your mind in roughly the same form, and vice versa. What are the mental and psychological processes that enable this tranference, when we aren&amp;rsquo;t physically wired together? I am interested in investigating the processes by which we recreate our mental states within other people - how we share and merge minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./intercomm.png&#34; alt=&#34;intercomm&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Group Mental Processes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under conditions of successful communication, groups of people can potentially function like one emergent organism. Much as one person&amp;rsquo;s brain solves complex tasks by integrating separate but complementary function across a network of brain regions, groups of people may also organize themselves into a larger cognitive unit by aligning themselves to a superordinate goal, dividing up subtasks, relegating certain functions to certain members, etc. I am also interested in studying how small groups organize their cognitive functioning for the purpose of completeing a joint task, and what sort of behavioral and neural patterns between people predict better group performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Fig34.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;groupbrainnetwork&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neuroscience of Social Influence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in my graduate career I focused on studying the neural markers of social influence. In particular, what are the brain signals that indicate persuasion? Can we use these signals to improve our predictions of behavioral change over and above self-report? And what do these particular signals say about how the process by which persuasion in the brain occurs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./persuasionbrain.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;persuasionbrain&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Naturalistic Neuroimaging in Social Neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social neuroscience is the study of neural processes in context - around other people, in certain moments, contingent on personal ideosyncracies, etc. But most neuroimaging methods in social neuroscience require participants to be alone and immobile, stripping most of the rich experience of everyday life from our experiments. So on top of my theoretical research interests, I have worked to situate functional near infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) as a useful tool for social neuroscience research, since it is a mobile neuroimaging device that can tolerate participant motion. In particular I have &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/smburns47&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;developed code&lt;/a&gt; for processing and analyzing fNIRS data, created &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLJqHk_LwA-fctJUP4zFzmL0cHCrzxz0MQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;workshop material&lt;/a&gt; to train new fNIRS researchers, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/kygbm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;written about&lt;/a&gt; the unique uses of fNIRS for social neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./fnirs.png&#34; alt=&#34;fnirs&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/smburns47/preprocessingfNIRS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;preprocessingfNIRS&lt;/a&gt; - Matlab and Python code that wraps our lab&amp;rsquo;s fNIRS preprocessing pipeline into one batch execution. Also includes a data quality check module. Not a fancy GUI, but should be commented enough that any competent Matlab or Python coder could dive into the pipeline and quickly change the parameters they want to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workshops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TEMNe5ROsw4&amp;amp;list=PLJqHk_LwA-fctJUP4zFzmL0cHCrzxz0MQ&amp;amp;index=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;fNIRS Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; - Series of Youtube videos that contain the fNIRS bootcamp lessons given to all new members of our lab. Contains some lab-specific info, but also a lot of generally useful lessons for all new and continuing fNIRS researchers. Periodically updated when code/procedures are changed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching Syllabi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/files/syllabus1.pdf&#34;&gt;The Psychology of the Mob: How and Why Groups Behave the Way They Do&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
